let us calculate the moment of inertia of
a disc. about an axis of rotation, which is
passing through the centre of disc. and it
is perpendicular to the plane of disc. as,
disk is a rigid body we can not directly calculate
its moment of inertia we first need to consider
an, element. and, by integration of moment
of inertia of elements of ring , over the
given range, will find the moment of inertia
of disc. here, for a disc we can consider
a small elemental rings, which are of radius
x, and width d x. like this. so if we consider
such elemental rings, which are of radius
x and having width d x, several such rings
when integrated from centre to. this circumference
of disc. we can say will be get the whole
disc. for this element, if says mass is d
m. we can write the mass of, element as. mass
of. elemental ring. is . this can be written
as mass per unit area multiplied by the area
occupied by this ring. so the total mass of
disc is m and its radius is r. here we can
say its mass per unit area is m by pie r square.
multiplied with the area occupied by the disc
. which can be given as, its length, into
the. width, that can be written as two pie
x, d x. as we can see we cut the ring and
flatten it. its , length will be two pie x
and width can be taken as d x. so in this
situation the mass of this element will write
as m by r square into two x d x. now if it
is a ring, as we can see this is a ring , the
moment of inertia . of the elemental ring.
can be given as. d i, which can be written
as d m x square. so in this situation as we
have, just now studied moment of inertia for
ring we can write as m r square , so for a
ring having mass d m and radius x moment of
inertia can be written as, d m x square. this
we can write as , just we substitute the value
of d m over here. will be two m by r square,
multiplied by x cube d x. now total moment
of inertia . of whole disc. can be given by
integration of all such elements , which is
integration of d i m we can write it integration
of two m by r square into x cube d x. and
we substitute the limits of integration from
zero to , r. now here, mass and radius of
the disc can be taken as constant , here only
variable is x. so integration of x cube can
be, taken as directly x four by four, and
we put the limits from zero to r. here we
can see will get it, two m by r square into,
r four by four minus zero. so here this two
gets cancelled out and r square gets cancelled
out , will get the moment of inertia of disc
to be. half m r square. this is the standard
result for moment of inertia for disc, about
an axis of rotation which is passing through
its centre and perpendicular to the, plane
of disc